大家好 我是《每日宇航员》的Tim Dodd
Hi it's me Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
商业航天工业在发射逃逸系统方面有一个大趋势
There's a new trend going around in the commercial space industry when it comes to launch abort systems.
三家商业航天公司的载人飞船逃逸系统
All 3 commercial companies who are putting abort systems on their crewed vehicles
都放弃了过去传统方式的逃逸塔
have ditched that classic launch abort tower we've seen dominate abort systems in the past.
之前的飞船比如水星号 阿波罗 甚至联盟号飞船都使用的是
Previous vehicles like The Mercury capsule, The Apollo capsule and even the Soyuz capsule all used
放置在载人舱段上方的逃逸塔
an escape tower that sat on top of the crew module.
可以在火箭发射失败时快速将飞船拽离火箭
Capable of pulling the vehicle away from a failing rocket in a hurry.
而这个话题更有趣的是
And to make this topic even more interesting
我们发现另一个逃逸系统的趋势是
we're seeing another trend in abort systems.
太空叉的载人龙飞船和波音的星际线飞船
SpaceX's crew Dragon capsule and Boeing Starliner capusles,
都使用了液体发动机而不是固体火箭发动机
both are using liquid filled abort motors instead of solid rocket motors.
那么今天我们将探讨太空叉 波音 蓝色起源的载人飞船
So today we're gonna at talk about the design considerations that have made
放弃传统逃逸塔背后的设计考虑
SpaceX, Boeing and Blue Origin ditch abort towers on their crewd vehicles
并重新评估波音和太空叉选择液体火箭发动机而不是固体燃料的原因
and we're also going to re-evaluate why the heck are Boeing and SpaceX
going with liquid rocket motors instead of solid rocket motors.
波音和太空叉的液体燃料逃逸系统都遇到了严重挫折和困难
And with both SpaceX and Boeing having experienced serious setbacks and complications
with their liquid fueled abort systems
其中包括损失一艘测试飞船
including the loss of a test vehicle.
就让大家怀疑这是个好主意吗
It raises the question, is it even a good idea?
这背后每一个系统都有很多工程上的决定 我们开始吧！
Now there's a lot of fun engineering decisions behind each and every system, so lets get started.
我以前已经聊过不少发射逃逸系统的内容了
I've talked about abort systems quite a bit in the past.
我有一期视频讲过为何太空叉的载人龙飞船在下部舱段(trunk)有小翼
I have a video explaining why SpaceX's Crew Dragon capsule has fins on the trunk.
这有助于飞船在逃逸过程中头部向上 尾焰向下
Which helped keep it pointing up and flaming down in the even of an abort.
我还有一期视频讲过
And I have another video talking about
为何双子号飞船使用的是弹射座椅而不是逃逸塔
why the gemini capsule went with an ejection seat instead of a launch abort tower.
那么我们先来简单介绍一下逃逸系统
So for a short run through on mechanical abort systems, here's a brief overview.
如果你坐在一个摩天大楼那么大的窜天猴上
If you're sitting on top of a skyscraper full of explosive materials
那么发生意外时就应该有一个快速逃生的办法
it's generally considered a good idea to have a way to evacuate quickly if things go wrong.
原本逃逸系统的工作原理是
The way abort systems originally worked
火箭燃料箱从头到尾放置有很多对导线
was by having a trail of wires running down the entire length of the tanks of the rocket.
一旦任何一对被切断
If any two of them are severed
就会触发逃逸系统点燃发动机
it triggered an abort system to fire up the motors
并将乘员舱段在一秒内分离
and detach the crew module within a fraction of a second.
逃逸发动机需要推力足够大
The abort motors have to be powerful enough
从而保证尽快将飞船拽离故障火箭
to pull the vehicle away from a failing rocket as quickly as possible.
该系统几秒内加速度可达15G
These systems can pull up to 15Gs of accelaration for a few seconds.
这可不好玩 实际上很糟糕
Now I'm not saying that sounds like fun but that actually sounds awful.
简直就是被半挂车连续撞几秒的感觉 我可不想体验
It sounds like been hit by a semi-truck for a few seconds continuely, yeah no thanks.
并且自从人类航天飞行早期阶段 至少在美国
And since the very beginning of human space flight, well at least in the United States,
工程师们选择的是在飞船顶部安装发射逃逸塔
engineer's opted for a launch escape tower stuck on top of the capsule.
你会看到一些脚手架一样的东西上装有强力火箭发动机
You'll notice some fancy scaffolding with a few really powerful rocket motors attached to it.
然后下面可能是水星号飞船 阿波罗飞船
On top of the Mercury Capsule, the Apollo capsule.
联盟号飞船 中国的神舟飞船
The Soyuz capsule, China's Shenzhou capsule
以及即将到来的猎户座飞船
as well as the upcoming Orion capsule
和印度的Gaganyaan飞船
and India's Gaganyaan capsule.
这些飞船的逃逸系统都使用固体火箭发动机
All of these vehicles also used solid rocket motors in the abort system
在那种小尺寸下推力非常大
because solid rocket motors are very powerful for their size.
它们可以立即点火
They can be lit in an instant.
结构简单 不工作时放置相对安全
They're simple and are relatively safe to have sitting around idle.
这种有塔的构型叫拖式逃逸系统
This configuration with a tower is called a tractor of a puller system.
因其发动机位于飞船上方 拖拽飞船逃逸
Since the motors are in front of the vehicle and they pull the vehicle free
与绝大多数位于火箭底部 推动火箭前进的发动机不同
as opposed to most rocket motors which are  at the bottom end of the vehicle and they push it.
三款最新的载人飞船都选择了
The three newest capsules that will be carrying humans to space have opted
放弃拖式逃逸系统
to ditch the tractor abort systems
且都选择了另一种名为“推式”的逃逸系统
and go with a different approach called a pusher system.
更有趣的是 太空叉 波音和蓝色起源
And even more interestingly SpaceX, Boeing and Blue Origin
各自的原因完全不同
all have wildly different reasons for doing so.
我们先从蓝色起源的新薛帕德飞船开始
So let's start off with Blue Origin and their New Shepard capsule.
新薛帕德飞船是亚轨道旅行竞赛中两名参赛者之一
New Shepard is one of two players in the sub-orbital tourism game.
对手是维珍银河的两架太空飞机
Competing with Virgin Galactic and their Spaceship two Space Plane
但蓝色起源的新薛帕德飞船是唯一拥有逃逸系统的
but Blue Origin's New Shepard is the only one of these two that offers an abort system.
蓝色起源的逃逸系统选择的是固体火箭发动机
The abort system that Blue Origin decided to go with is solid rocket motor
安装在飞船中央
placed smack in the middle of their capsule
在一个看着像个漂亮的桌子下面
underneath what looks like a beautiful table
但它其实是一个装有固体火箭发动机的大型耐爆炸高压管
but is actually a large chunk of blast resistant and high pressured tubing holding the solid rocket motor.
之前提到这属于推式逃逸系统
As mentioned before this makes it a pusher system
因为逃逸时尾气从飞船底部喷出
since the exhaust comes out of the bottom of the vehicle when used during an abort.
这个系统有趣的一点是它使用的时候看上去很不稳定
Now an interesting note with this system is how wobbly it looks when in use.
这很有可能是因为它推力的重心与自身重心太近了
This is likely because the center of thrust is very close to the center of mass
使其本身稳定性较差
making it inherently less stable.
这在我之前讲龙飞船为何在trunk上有小翼的视频中提过此事
I talked about this briefly in the video about why the Crew Dragon capsule has fins on the trunk.
这么一说 新薛帕德火箭貌似可以使用某些气动性质来让自身更加稳定
Saying it looks like New Shepard could use some aero-services to help keep it more stable
当然啦 只要飞船远离了火箭 基本就安全了
but then again as long as it get's the heck out of there, it's probably fine.
蓝色起源的逃逸系统使用固体火箭是合理的
Blue Origins use of a solid rocket booster makes sense for this abort system.
因为它只会在紧急情况下使用
Since it's only to be used in emergency.
它就是摆在那 并且希望永远不会派上用场
It just kinda hangs out there hoping to never need to be used.
固体火箭发动机某些性质非常好
Something a solid rocket motor does perfectly.
它储存安全 且推重比高 使用起来很无脑
It's high thrust to weight ratio and safe storage makes it a no-brainer for this.
那么问题来了 为什么他们不用传统的逃逸塔呢？
So now we can ask ourselves, why didn't they go with a more traditional escape tower?
首先 新薛帕德飞船目标是
First off, The New Shepard is trying to
廉价 可多次快速发射 完全可复用
operate as inexpensively and frequently as possible by being fully re-usable.
它的助推器可以靠自身反推完成惊人的着陆
It's booster very impressively lands itself propusively
飞船用安全可靠的降落伞进行软着陆
and the capusle relies on safe and reliable parachutes to make a soft touchdown.
游戏的规则是尽可能少甚至不进行翻新
The name of the game is little to no refurbishment.
而逃逸塔通常是要被抛弃的
A lauch abort tower is traditionally jettisoned
这样在其可使用的时间段过后可以减少飞船死重
once it's useful window of operation has passed to free up dead weight from the vehicle.
但对于本身就直上直下的亚轨道系统
But with a sub-orbital system that only goes straight up and straight back down.
你可能认为它们可以把逃逸塔留着不扔
You'd think they'd probably just keep the tower on.
这倒也没错 因为飞船顶部没有要露出来的对接口
And this is espcially true since there's no docking port that would need to be uncovered
因为新薛帕德飞船不会和任何东西对接
because their New Shepard vehicle doesn't dock with anything
可假如说你留着逃逸塔在上面
but say you did leave it on,
那你可不想在有逃逸塔的时候开降落伞
it's pretty safe to say you wouldn't wanna deploy your parachutes in the vicinity of that launch escape tower
因为有很大的缠住伞绳的风险
because there'd be a pretty big risk of them getting tangled up in it.
所以对于逃逸塔来说
So in the case of a launch abort tower
任务成功需要逃逸塔能成功脱离 否则降落伞就无法正常工作了
mission success relies on that tower being ditched or else the parachutes won't work correctly.
于是问题来了
So that raises the question,
设计一个需要每次飞行都进行分离才能成功的系统是否更好？
is it better to design a system that requires a separation
event every single flight in order to be successful?
还是说你想设计一个只需要在紧急情况下启动的系统？
Or do you wanna design a system that only needs to be used in an emergency?
别忘了 蓝色起源可不想在飞行中抛弃逃逸塔
And besides that Blue Origin wouldn't want to ditch the abort tower in flight
因为它落点可能离自家厂房太近
since it could land pretty close to their facilties
每次飞行都有砸坏自家厂房的风险 这也会增加成本
and it would be likely destroyed with each and every flight, which would add to the cost
但蓝色起源使用推式系统可能还有一个更重要的原因
but there's perhaps even a bigger reason why Blue Origin went with pusher system.
相当相当重要的原因
And by bigger, I mean bigger.
观察这些拖式逃逸系统
Take a look at these puller systems.
你有没有发现少了什么
Do you notice anything missing?
拖式系统几乎都有一个保护性的罩子
Puller systems almost always have a protective faring or a shell
会挡住飞船的窗户
that covers the windows
从而在逃逸系统启动时保护飞船本身
and the rest of the vehicle to protect the vehicle if the abort system is used.
大体上讲 把窗户遮住是为了保证它不被尾焰吹黑吹坏
It'd generally be a good idea to make sure your windows
are covered up so you don't completely obliterate them.
水星号飞船逃逸塔没有遮住窗户
The Mercury capsules had a window and an escape tower
那是因为水星号飞船的逃逸塔发动机比其他的位置更高
but on the Mercury capsule the motors were much higher up on the tower than other systems.
早期人类航天个别事情会和现在有所区别
And we did things a little differently in the early days of human space flight
放到今天可能就很迷惑
that might just be frowned upon today.
既然拖式逃逸发动机和大窗户不可兼得
Since puller abort motors and windows don't typically go hand in hand,
那遮住世界上飞往太空的最大的窗户就太丢人了
covering up world's largest windows that go to space would be a pretty big shame.
新薛帕德飞船旨在提供拥有震撼视野的太空旅行体验
Since New Shepards entire purpose is to provide the ultimate tourist experience with stunning views.
他们当然会把透过巨大窗户看外面这个要求放在首位
They sure wanna make sure seeing out those big, giant, beautiful windows is a top priority.
所以对于蓝色起源来说 使用固体火箭发动机的推式逃逸系统就很合理了
So for Blue Origin the use of a pusher type solid rocket motor abort system makes the most sense.
接下来我们说说波音的星际线飞船和太空叉的载人龙飞船
Next up, let's talk about Boeing's Starliner and SpaceX's Crew Dragon Capsules
它们都是设计给NASA运送宇航员到国际空间站用的
which both were designed for NASA to send crews up to the International Space Station.
它们现在是专门设计用于往返国际空间站的飞船
Now these are purpose built taxis to the ISS first and foremost
但以后某天它们可能都会接一些商业的私活
although both vehicles may seek commercial use someday for private customers.
我有一期视频详细介绍了这两种飞船和发射它们的火箭
I have a video that dives really deep into both of these vehicles and the rockets they ride on
我还把它们和另外两款可以前往空间站的飞船——航天飞机与联盟号作比较
and then I compared them to the space shuttle and Soyuz, the other vehicles that visit the ISS.
如果你需要了解下前情提要 了解下这些飞船的参数与设计考量
So if you need a rundown on what the history is, the specs and all of the considerations of these vehicles,
欢迎前去观看往期视频
definitely check this video out.
太空叉的龙飞船与波音的星际线飞船也都使用了推式系统
Both SpaceX's Crew Dragon capsule and Boeing's Starliner opted to use a pusher system too.
它们都没有选择逃逸塔的方案
They've chosen to ditch the tower
它们都转而选择了液体燃料驱动的逃逸发动机
but both of these cheicles opted to use liquid fueled abort motors
而没有选择更加传统的固体火箭发动机
instead of the more traditional solid rocket motors.
你现在可能会奇怪
Now you might be thinking,
液体火箭发动机怎么做到在紧急情况下快速安全可靠地逃逸呢
how can a liquid fueled rocket engine be quick and safe enough
to be relied upon for an emergency abort.
毕竟 火箭发动机需要花费数秒让泵转起来 之后才能点火
After all, rocket engines can take several seconds to get the pumps spinning and for ignition to occur
所以……听起来这个选择不是很好
so that doesn't really sound like a good option.
实际上 它们使用的液体火箭发动机
Well, these liquid fueled rocket engines
更像是RCS使用的发动机
are using a similar system to what's used in reaction controlled systems
可以快速可靠地点火
which offer very quick and reliable ignition.
实现方法是使用一种无需燃料泵的挤压供应发动机
They do this by using utilizing a pumpless rocket engine known as a pressure fed engine.
挤压供应发动机只需要把燃料储存在一个高压罐中
Pressure fed engines just have their propellants stored in a very high pressure tank.
开一个阀门 就能直接喷
They open a valve and they let it rip.
为了提高其可靠性
And to make it even more reliable
它们逃逸系统所用的挤压供应发动机使用的是自燃推进剂
the pressure fed engines used on these abort motors run on hypergolic propellants.
自燃推进剂会在两种燃料接触时自动燃烧
Hypergolic propellants burn on contact with each other
所以不需要额外的点火源
so there's no need for a secondary ignition source like a spark or a flame.
这使得挤压供应自燃推进剂发动机结构简单 反应快速 可靠性高
This makes the pressure fed hypergolic engine very simple, quick acting and reliable.
是逃逸发动机与RCS的不二选择
A great choice for reaction control and abort motors.
还要注意的是 虽然自燃推进剂非常稳定可靠
It should also be noted that although hypergolic fuels are very stable and reliable,
但它们都是剧毒的 高致癌的可怕物质
they're incredibly toxic, Cancerogenic and just really nasty stuff.
那么为什么波音和太空叉选择了液体燃料逃逸发动机呢？
So why did both companies choose liquid fueled abort motors?
原因有很多 但最重要的可能是由于NASA对安全性的要求提高了。
There's a few reasons but first and foremost it's likely due to increased safety requirements from NASA.
他们想要的是所谓的全包络逃逸系统或从飞行中任何一点安全逃逸的能力
They wants what's known as full envelope abort system or the ability to abort safely from any point in the flight.
当然 固体燃料发动机也能提供该选项
Now solid rocket motors can provide this option too.
目前 猎户座飞船的拖式系统的固体火箭发动机可以提供前两分钟的逃逸
For instance, the Orion capsule solid rocket tractor system offers an abort mode for the first two minutes of flight
之后逃逸塔会被抛掉
after which the tower is jettisoned
SLS二级或者服务舱的AJ10发动机也能提供逃逸功能
and the second stage of the SLS system or the service modules AJ 10 engine can provide abort options.
而使相比于固体燃料 用液体燃料逃逸发动机可以降低燃烧时间或推力
But with liquid fueled abort motors they can fire them for less time or lower thrust than a solid rocket motor
让发动机能更好地将飞船送入预定路线
which gives them the ability to place the vehicle precisely into a desired trajectory
可能是安全再入 可能是放弃入轨
to either re-enter safely or abort to orbit.
这样就更容易设计一个全包络逃逸系统窗口
Which can make it easier to design a full envelope abort window.
但讲道理 两家公司都大可选用典型的固体火箭拖式逃逸系统
But quite frankly each company could have gone with a typical tractor solid rocket motor abort system.
实际上 太空叉最初龙飞船——当时叫龙骑士——的概念中
As a matter of fact, SpaceX's original concepts for the Crew Dragon capsule
or Dragon Rider as they called it back then
就要使用传统逃逸塔 并在上升阶段抛弃 就像他们2010的动画演示中那样
was going to utilize a traditional tower and then jettison it on ascent as we can see in this animation from 2010.
所以两家公司选用推式逃逸系统的原因就如前文所说
So the first reason each company opted for a pusher system is the same reason we talked about before.
减少一个分离事件 就能减少一分潜在的任务失败风险
By removing a separation event, you're eliminating a potential mission failure scenario.
把逃逸系统嵌入到飞船本身
By intergrating the abort system into the vehicle
可以简化发射流程 提升成功率
it simplifies sequence of events needed for mission success.
但逃逸系统集成进飞船不代表就非得用液体燃料啊
But integrating the abort system doesn't necessarily mean they have to use liquid fuels, does it?
你看 新薛帕德飞船就用的固体燃料
I mean, New Shepard get's away with it.
使用液体燃料逃逸发动机实际上更有用有两个原因
Well there's two reasons why utilizing liquid fuel abort motors in these cases are actually more usefull
甚至对于集成式逃逸系统来说是必须的
or even necessary in an integrated abort system.
第一个原因是控制
The first reason is control.
液体燃料发动机可以让飞船转向
Liquid fuel rocket motors can steer
通过推力差来让飞船指向特定方向
and point the vehicle by doing something called thrust differential
具体是通过增加或减少某台发动机的推力
which is where they can increase or decrease thrust on any of the motors
从而帮助飞船指向正确方向
and that can help point it in the correct way.
这对飞船头朝上尾焰朝下有很大帮助
This definitely helps keep the pointy end up and the flaming end down.
的确有几种办法控制固体火箭发动机 但推力差不在其中
Now there are ways to control a solid rocket motor but thrust differential isn't one of them.
所以想让固体火箭逃逸塔转向
So in order to steer a solid abort tower
一种很帅的方法是使用多出口的固体火箭
one cool way is by having a separate solid motor fire
让逃逸塔一圈的多个阀门开启或关闭
and having multiple valves open and close on each side of the tower.
来看看猎户座的姿态控制发动机测试
Take a look at this Orion attitude control motor test.
里面是一个点火后的固体火箭发动机
Inside there is a solid rocket motor that
一旦点火就无法关闭
lights and cannot be turned off once activated
想要控制转向
but in order to provide steering,
可以控制尾焰从八个出口出来的多少
they can vary how much thrust comes out of any of it's eight valves.
想要直着飞 那就全部八个等大开启
To provide neutral input they just open up all eight valves equally
所有力相互抵消就不会转向了
which then will produce no change in direction.
然后他们把这个装置放到逃逸塔顶端
They then stick this unit really high up on the abort tower
从而提供最大的转向力矩
to provide maximum leverage over the vehicle
以便在逃逸过程中提供充足的控制
which helps provide ample control during the abort.
我觉得挺帅的
I think this is really cool.
在推式系统中 没有塔来提供那么大的转向力矩
In a pusher system there's no tower to provide leverage
所以顶上就没地方放控制单元
so you can't put control services up there.
所以使用无法控制推力大小的固体火箭发动机就不太合适
So using a solid rocket motor that can't provide thrust differential can be a bit of a no-no.
但这两艘飞船无法使用固体逃逸发动机还有第二个原因
But there's actually another reason why you can't use solid rocket motors on these two vehicles.
那就是它们还要去国际空间站
And that's because these vehicles visit the International Space Station
而因为它们要去国际空间站
and because they visit the International Space Station
逃逸发动机就也要跟着去空间站
the abort motors also visit the station.
这意味着飞船每天要经受32次昼夜巨大的温差变化
This means 32 times a day the vehicle has extreme changes in temperature or thermal cycles.
使用自燃推进剂就没什么问题 因为它们在这些情况下仍然很稳定
Now hypergolics are happy as a clam and stable hanging out in these conditions.
实际上 此时此刻空间站上就存有自燃推进剂
As a matter of fact, there's hypergolics on the station as we speak.
火箭发动机每天剧烈的温度变化
The thermal cycling of a rocket motor that much
可能会有潜在的爆炸风险
could potentially lead to some unintended booms.
你肯定不想拿个炸弹和世界上最昂贵的 上面还载有人的单体建筑去对接
And that's definetely not a good thing when you're attached to the single most expensive piece of machinery
with precious human lives on board.
那两家公司又为何费劲去把逃逸系统整合进飞船上呢？
So why are they even bothering integrating the launch abort system at all?
这听上去挺费力不讨好啊
This all sounds like an awful lot of trouble.
除了之前说的 集成进飞船后 发射可以少一步分离
Besides the simplicity of an integrated system not needing to separate,
两家公司选择集成逃逸系统实际上还有各自不同的理由
the two companies actually have very different reasons for their integration.
波音改装了Aerojet Rocketdyne的RS-88发动机 使其使用与RCS相同的燃料
Boeing modified some Aerojet Rocketdyne RS-88 Bantam motors to run on the same fuel as the reaction control system
而RCS正是星际线飞船服务舱的一部分
that is part of the service modules of Starliner
这样就不用使用原来的液氧酒精作为燃料了
instead of the alcohol and liquid oxygen they normally use.
服务舱还装有太阳帆板和飞船的散热器
The service module also houses the solar panels and radiators of the vehicle.
通过使用和RCS相同的燃料进行逃逸
By using the same fuel for the abort and the reaction control systems
意味着没有启动逃逸系统的常规任务有了更多额外燃料可以使用
it means an anominal mission the abort system obviously isn't utilized
意味着如果逃逸系统没有启动 常规任务就有了更多额外燃料可以使用
which means the extra propellent can be used for other things.
除了有更多的燃料能用于在轨机动
Besides having more fuel for orbital maneuvering
多余的燃料还可以给国际空间站提升轨道
you also end up with spare propellent to potentially reboost the International Space Station.
而这目前只有俄罗斯的进步号补给船和天鹅号补给船能做到
Now this is something only Russia's Progress supply vehicle and the Cygnus cargo vehicle can currently do.
已经退役的航天飞机和ATV飞船之前也能做到
But the retired space shuttle and the ATV vehicle could also do it previously.
有能力给空间站升轨 绝对是个卖点
Having the ability to reboost the station is definetely a nice selling point.
虽然星际线能不能落实此事我们没有确切消息
Although we don't have any confirmation on whether or not Starliner will ever perform this maneuver
但至少有这能力总不是坏事
but atleast having it is isn't a bad option at all.
但对于太空叉来说 他们不想抛弃逃逸发动机的最大原因
But for SpaceX, perhaps their biggest reason why they didn't wanna ditch their motors
是他们的龙飞船设计是要复用尽可能多的次数
is 'cause they designed the Dragon capsule to be reused as much as possible.
这意味着 他们可以把逃逸发动机集成到飞船上后
This means by integrating the abort motors with the capsule itself,
他们每次飞行都可以回收发动机
they would recover them with each flight.
但讽刺的是 龙飞船复用性还不如星际线飞船
But ironically the Dragon capsule is less reusable than the Starliner
因为载人龙飞船是溅落海面的 而星际线飞船是陆地着陆
since the Crew Dragon capsule splashes down as opposed to the Starliner which will land on land.
这意味着载人龙飞船复用无法载人
This means that the Crew Dragon capusle will never be never be reused for crew
只能拉货
and will only be used as a cargo vessel.
更搞笑的是 星际线采用陆地着陆 可以复用十次
And what's even more ironic is the Starliner which lands on land and can be reused up to 10 times
每次飞行却要抛弃逃逸发动机
ditches it's abort motors with each and every flight.
因为安装逃逸发动机的服务舱在再入前要抛掉
As the service module which houses the abort motors is jettisoned before re-entry.
所以陆地着陆的飞船会扔掉逃逸发动机
So the vehicle which lands on land ditches it's abort motors
海面溅落的飞船则会留下逃逸发动机
and the one that lands in the ocean keeps it's abort motors.
有意思吧
That's interesting.
但太空叉龙飞船最初选用超级天龙座液体发动机
But the main reason why SpaceX's Crew Dragon has the super Draco liquid fuel abort motors in the first place
并不单纯是为逃逸考虑
isn't just for abort options.
他们原本打算让龙飞船反推着陆
They originally intended to land the Dragon capsule propulsively.
你没听错 他们原本打算让龙飞船像太空叉的猎鹰九号和重型猎鹰回收那样着陆
Yes that's right, they originally intended to land the Dragon Capsule much like SpaceX
lands it's Falcon9 and Falcon Heavy Rockets.
脚踩四条烈焰 帅呆了
Riding pillars of flames, so cool.
而最初选择反推着陆的原因是为了让飞船快速复用
Now the original reason for landing propulsively was for rapid and easy reuse of the vehicle.
除此之外 他们还想让龙飞船在火星着陆
Not only that but they also wanted the Dragon capsule to land on Mars.
太空叉的原本目标是让龙飞船改装成为“红龙”飞船后执行一次火星任务
SpaceX's original goal with the Dragon was to land it on Mars for a mission dubbed Red Dragon
但整个反推着陆的计划被毙了
but the whole propulsive landing idea got scrapped.
太空叉放弃研究龙飞船反推着陆主要原因
SpaceX gave up on pursuing propulsive landing with the Dragon capsule
是NASA爸爸对这概念实在不感冒
mostly because NASA really wasn't interested in the concept.
因为这需要相当多额外的认证工作
As it would require far too much additional work to certify.
现在我们讲了为什么三家公司都放弃了逃逸塔
So now that we've talked about why each company ditched the tower
且为什么波音和太空叉选择了液体燃料的发射逃逸系统
and why both Boeing and SpaceX has opted to use liquid fuelled propellent's for it's launch abort systems.
那么问题来了 这是个好主意吗？
It raises the question, is it even a good idea?
波音和太空叉在测试他们的液体火箭逃逸系统中都遇到了麻烦
Both Boeing and SpaceX have had problems when testing their liquid abort systems.
在2018年 波音的星际线测试飞船遇到过异常
Boeing experienced an anomily with a Starliner test vehicle in 2018
当时他们在准备进行发射台逃逸测试 自燃推进剂发生了泄漏
when preparing to do a pad abort test, where the hypergolic fuels leaked out of the vehicle.
太空叉在2019年出的事就更牛逼了
SpaceX had something a little more energetic happen in 2019
他们在准备用回收后的DM-1载人龙飞船进行飞行中逃逸测试前的静态点火
when preparing to do a static fire test prior to an in-flight abort test
abort test with their recovered DM-1 Crew Dragon capsule.
我个人认为这些问题都会解决
In my opinion these issues will get worked out.
这些燃料 这些系统和全世界几乎所有航天器使用的非常相似
These fuels using these systems are the same or very similar to almost all orbital spacecraft.
毕竟 连卫星也在用液体的自燃推进剂进行在轨机动
After all, satellites often use hypergolic fuels and a liquid motor to do their orbital maneuvering.
航天飞机的轨道机动系统(OMS)使用的是自燃推进剂
The space shuttle had hypergolic fuels for it's orbital maneuvering system
货运龙飞船也使用自燃推进剂飞了十多次
and hypergolics are already used on Dragon-1 for well over a dozen missions.
而这些系统几乎没出过问题
And there rarely has been any issues with these systems.
简言之 这些系统安全 简单 可靠
In general these systems can be safe, simple and reliable.
那为何在测试中会遇到这么严重的问题？
So why are we seeing such major problems arise when testing them?
对外的回答通常是 “测试就是为了这个”
Well the public relation answer is, that's why we test.
但我通常认为原因出在测试方式上
But I kind of have a feeling it has to do with how you test this stuff.
测试时的条件通常是远超正常范围
You often times go beyond what you'd normally be doing.
而测试时所做的事情在正常发射台上可能八百年见不到一次
And doing things in these testing campaigns that wouldn't normally be done on the launch pad.
至于这是不是好主意 我的答案是肯定的
As far as is it a good idea, I mean I think so.
燃料本来就在飞船上 那不如用它逃逸吧
The fuels are already on the vehicle in the first place so it makes sense to use them for a launch abort system.
液体燃料逃逸系统很有用
Liquid fueled abort systems are useful.
它们有潜在的复用价值 可以简化航天器 简化发射流程
Potentially reusable and actually make for a simpler spacecraft and mission profile.
而且不用的话 还能拿来干别的事
Not to mention, when they're not used they can be utilized for other purposes
比如给空间站升轨甚至反推着陆
such as reboosting the ISS or even propulsively landing.
虽然我们可能永远见不到这两件事的发生了
Although we probably won't ever see either of those things happen.
我相信两家公司都已经从这些系统的故障教训中有所改进
I'm sure each company is learning from the failures of these systems
我也毫不怀疑在我们送人上天前这些问题都会被解决
and I have little doubt this will all be sorted out before we ever put humans on board.
希望能早日解决吧！
And hopefully that's sooner rather than later.
所以今天很有意思 我们从以前传统的逃逸系统
So it is interesting that we went from one common form of launch abort
突然来到21世纪三家公司使用了截然不同的逃逸系统
to suddenly three 21st century companies using widly different systems.
再一细品发现 每家公司这些工程上的决策背后原因却都不相同
But in the long run each company has a unique reason behind their engineering decisions.
我感觉挺有意思
Which I find fun.
所以这是否回答了大家的问题——为什么他们都放弃了逃逸塔？
So does this help answer your questions of why companies have scrapped abort towers?
以及有两家为什么使用的是液体火箭发动机？
Or why they're now using liquid fueled rocket motors?
如果大家在这个话题上还有什么其他问题 欢迎在评论区留言
Let me know if you have any other questions about this topic in the comments below.
另外既然说到了逃逸系统的未来趋势
In keeping with this trend of talking about escape systems,
我正在计划做一期视频讲为何太空叉不打算在将来的Starship上安装逃逸系统
I plan on making a video about why SpaceX doesn't plan to use an abort system on their upcoming Starship
并解答这是否是个好主意这样的问题
and help answer the question of whether or not that's a good idea.
非常感谢我所有Patreon上的赞助者帮助我完成本期视频以及其他内容
I owe a huge thanks to all my patreon supporters for helping me make videos like this
and all other content possible.
Patreon的赞助者可以进入专门的Reddit子版块与Discord群
Patreon members get exclusive access to a sub-Reddit and a Discord channel
还能看到专属直播内容 提前看到某些视频内容
as well as excluive live-streams and early access to some videos.
所以如果大家想支持我所做的
So if you wanna help support what I do
请前往下方链接
please head on over to patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
顺便别忘了看看我的网店 最近有不少有意思的新货
And while you're online be sure to check out my web store for lot's of fun new merchandise
比如太空叉格栅舵风格的杯垫和我这样的帽子
such as Gridfin coasters, hats like this.
海报 和我穿的这件T恤
Prints, maybe t-shirts like this.
很多有意思的东西 店铺链接在下面
Lots of other fun stuff at everydayastronaut.com/shop.
与往常一样 我视频中所有的音乐都是原创的
As always, all the music in my videos is original
你可以在Spotify iTunes Amazon或Google Music上听我的一些音乐
and you can listen to some of my music on Spotify or iTunes or Amazon or Google Music.
任何你想听音乐的时候
Or really wherever you listen to music.
都可以去下方链接听 记得分享给朋友
For easy links, got to everydayastronaught.com/music and share it with a friend.
感谢大家观看 我是《每日宇航员》的Tim Dodd
Thanks everybody, that does it for me, I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
把太空知识带入寻常百姓家
Bringing space down to earth for every day people.